# Mahmood Syed

Atlanta Metropolitan Area



linkedin.com/in/mahmood-syed-712205188



msyed0230@gmail.com



864-631-7058

## Summary

Looking to contribute 5+ years of life sciences research experience, strong communication skills as evidenced by multiple lectures/presentations given, and excellent leadership skills formed from mentoring students to an interdisciplinary team where my experience and education cultivates both personal and professional growth.

## Experience



## **Quality Control Chemist/Regulatory Compliance Specialist**

Synerzine

Aug 2019 - Present (11 months +)



#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

**Emory University** 

Aug 2017 - Aug 2019 (2 years 1 month)

Worked under Dr. Nathan Jui.

Conducted multi-step synthetic chemistry toward the design of novel positron emission tomography (PET) radiotracers.

- -Individually led a collaborative project between Emory (Jui laboratory) and the Winship Cancer Institute (Goodman laboratory) to create 18F-labeled 5-aminolevulinic acid (5ALA) derivatives serving as diagnostic tools for brain tumor development.
- -Advanced materials up to cell study stage to evaluate uptake of labeled 5ALA derivatives in both rat and human tumor cells.
- -EHSO-approved for Radiation Studies at Wesley Woods Health Center; obtained hands-on experience with conducting radiolabeling studies of PET radiotracers.
- -Designed and presented lectures to organic chemistry students about laboratory methods such as extractions and recrystallization. Responsible for supervising and setting up organic chemistry lab guiding undergraduate students through several laboratory modules.
- -Prepared and presented lectures to research group on advanced chemistry subject matters, including total syntheses of complex natural products and novel catalytic reaction methodologies.

## Undergraduate Research Assistant

**Furman University** 

May 2017 - Jul 2017 (3 months)

Worked under Dr. Greg Springsteen.

Researched prebiotic origins of known enzymatic processes in the context of essential cofactors.

-Independent design, research, and analysis into the abiotic synthesis of thiamine pyrophosphate (TPP), leading to discovery of potentially key intermediate 1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate.

#### Biochemistry Teaching Assistant

**Furman University** 

Jan 2017 - May 2017 (5 months)

Worked under Dr. Karen Buchmueller.

-Supervised activity of students, managed general lab safety, assisted with laboratory techniques, answered questions, and maintained inventory of laboratory supplies (solvents, TLC stains, etc.).

## Undergraduate Chemistry Tutor

### **Furman University**

Apr 2015 - May 2017 (2 years 2 months)

Provided tutoring/mentoring services to undergraduate students spanning all chemistry courses

- -Held weekly tutoring sessions with students to help clarify subject matter from their courses.
- -Created collaborative environment by working alongside other chemistry tutors in the same location so students and tutors could help each other.
- -Consulted with professors of respective courses weekly to determine the focus of each tutoring session.

## Assistant for Office of Institutional Research

### **Furman University**

Feb 2014 - May 2017 (3 years 4 months)

Worked under Donald Pierce. Created a variety of documents to organize vast amount of data from student surveys, questionnaires, interviews, college statistics, etc. Also prepared surveys for the beginning and end of each school year. Accomplished tasks using primarily SPSS, Microsoft Word, and Microsoft Excel.

## Organic Chemistry Teaching Assistant

#### **Furman University**

Aug 2016 - Dec 2016 (5 months)

Worked under Dr. Greg Springsteen.

-Supervised activity of students, managed general lab safety, assisted with laboratory techniques, answered questions, and maintained inventory of laboratory supplies (solvents, TLC stains, etc.).

## Undergraduate Research Assistant

#### **Furman University**

May 2014 - Jul 2016 (2 years 3 months)

Worked under Dr. Sandy and Dr. John Wheeler.

Collaboration with the FDA on the activity of common biocides in the presence of commercial-brand contact lenses

- -Conducted in-depth experiments to examine rates of uptake/release of biocide polyhexamethylene biguanide in the presence of 12 commercial-brand contact lenses, addressing a public concern of eye infections such as keratitis.
- -Discovered high uptake rates onto contact lenses across all brands within 6 hours, correlating with substantial loss of antimicrobial activity of contact lens solutions and prompting the need for development of more bench-stable solutions.

### Store Clerk

## sweetFrog Frozen Yogurt

Jul 2011 - Aug 2013 (2 years 2 months)

Worked under Alisa Bridger. Responsible for greeting customers, managing cash register/purchases, maintaining a clean environment, prepping of yogurt toppings, addressing customer concerns, and advertising the business

#### **Education**



#### **Emory University**

Master's degree, Organic Chemistry

2017 - 2019

## **furman University**

Bachelor of Science - BS, Biochemistry

2013 - 2017

Participated in several extracurricular activities at Furman while also maintaining a high GPA (3.95)

#### **Honors & Awards**

## ☐ Bradshaw-Feaster Medal for General Excellence - Furman University

May 2017

Awarded to top male graduate of Class of 2017

## **Reeler Scholarship** - Furman University

Sep 2016

\$6000/yr. for chemistry majors demonstrating academic excellence (3.5 GPA or above)

## ☐ Wilson Endowment Scholarship - Furman University

Sep 2016

\$30,000/yr. for pre-medical students demonstrating academic excellence (3.5 GPA or above)

## Palmetto Fellows Scholarship - Furman University

Aug 2013

\$10,000/yr for incoming high school graduates demonstrating academic excellence (3.8 GPA or above)

## **Bell Tower Scholarship** - Furman University

Aug 2013

Bell Tower Scholarships support high-achieving students whose academic, co-curricular, community service, and/or leadership experiences suggest that they will make positive contributions to the Furman community. \$18,000/yr

#### **Skills**

Collaborative Leadership • Peer Mentoring • Open-mindedness • Data Analysis • Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (LC-MS) • Mass Spectrometry • Laboratory Skills • Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) • Organic Synthesis • Chemistry